<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Omanshu Thapliyal</title>
    <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Omanshu Thapliyal</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 11:57:21 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>On Eigenvalues, Homotopy, and Root Loci</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/circles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 11:57:21 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/circles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Consider an $$n+1$$ dimensional matrix as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;$$&#xA;A = \begin{pmatrix}&#xA;\frac{\pi^2}{6} &amp; 1 &amp; \frac{1}{4} &amp; ... &amp; \frac{1}{n^2} \\&#xA;1 &amp; \frac{\pi^2}{6} &amp; \frac{1}{4} &amp; ... &amp; \frac{1}{n^2} \\&#xA;\vdots &amp; &amp; \ddots &amp; &amp; \vdots\\&#xA;1 &amp; \frac{1}{4} &amp; ... &amp; \frac{1}{n^2}  &amp;\frac{\pi^2}{6} \\&#xA;\end{pmatrix} $$&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Is the matrix positive-definite?&#xA;The problem itself is a dramatization of how &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.purdue.edu/AAE/people/ptProfile?resource_id=1339&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;my professor&lt;/a&gt; would ask us to write arbitrary real matrices and quickly determine its positive-definiteness (most of the times) as a trick, seemingly like in-class wizardry!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reward is enough — when can we &#34;reinforce&#34; the learning?</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/reward-is-enough/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 11:07:46 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/reward-is-enough/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog post summarizes the papers &lt;strong&gt;Settling the Reward Hypothesis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Utility Theory for Sequential Decision Making&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;reward hypothesis&lt;/strong&gt; is at the core of Reinforcement Learning (RL) in that whether sequential action problems can be posed as some sort of a reward maximization.  One of the founders of modern RL, Richard S. Sutton, puts it as&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;That all of what we mean by goals and purposes can be well thought of as maximization of the expected value of the cumulative sum of a received scalar signal (reward).&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Technology Readiness Levels of AI methods</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/readiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 11:07:46 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/readiness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recent news of the SpaceX catching its Starship Super Heavy booster&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is quite discussed and marveled upon in the media, and rightly so.&#xA;Executing what was done can perhaps be explained as trying to catch a falling stick, then balancing it vertically, all while the stick is over 200 ft tall, weighs over 150 tonnes, spews fire, and costs over tens of millions of dollars.&#xA;One cannot but feel a little giddy as a controls engineering enthusiast over this massive success.&#xA;It makes me think why we are closer to automation in certain domains/problems than others? Why, for example, is your vacuum cleaning robot seemingly better at navigating in a cluttered environment than your possibly self-driving car? Why is the tremendous progress in machine learning &amp;amp; AI not permeating outside of our web lives as much as we expected in the early 2000&amp;rsquo;s?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why I am studying this: Data Driven Safety</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/data-driven-safety/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2022 12:32:31 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/data-driven-safety/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my attempt to try to motivate and justify why I am studying what I study, and to try to justify the title of my dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While most emphasis on safety has been provided from a model-driven perspective, data-driven approaches present a novel semi model-driven method by employing model-discovery. As data becomes more inexpensive, and system capabilities highly nonlinear, and often subject to parameter variations during mission, data-driven approaches are utilized more and more in controls engineering. Further, online and real-time applications increasingly require unknown models and nonlinear interactions to be learned for control synthesis. To this end, more established fields of system identification are increasingly utilizing data-driven models by using neural networks, autoregressive models, and other machine learning techniques. Due to the expressive nature of such machine learning techniques, they are  utilized to learn models of unknown dynamical systems from observed data sequences. In such approaches, a `discovered model&amp;rsquo; is arrived at using data, and employed to perform control design. Even though purely model-driven are slowly getting harder to apply to more recent, realistic, and complex scenarios, they provide a strong basis to study extensions of similar approaches to data-driven techniques for estimation and control. As a result, I attempt to utilize model-driven techniques and extend them to study safety and security properties of cyberphysical systems using data. Therefore, &lt;em&gt;my primary aim is to study data-driven approaches to safety, and data-driven vulnerabilities against cyberattacks, of complex control systems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Industry-Academia split in Control Systems</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/split/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2019 12:32:31 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/split/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I often wonder why the &amp;ldquo;cutting edge&amp;rdquo; research that we read about in the foremost scientific journals &amp;amp; conferences in Control Systems are never applied in the industry.&#xA;Because whenever we read/write papers, Section-I always tries to ground itself to industry and/or practical applications. However, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty well known that a majority of the controllers used in the industry are still tuned PIDs.&#xA;Even though sub-fields of modern control &amp;ndash; adaptive, and robust control are very mature and pretty old in their own rights, the real world&amp;rsquo;s inertia against using modern control techniques bears substantial weight.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MLP Approximation</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/mlp-approximation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2019 10:27:01 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/mlp-approximation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost always we hear about classification or machine learning problems, the go-to methods to solve the problem are neural networks, or multi-layered percetrons (MLP).&#xA;Now function approximation problems, which is what classification is, are very well defined in terms of consistency, accuracy, and other abilities of the approximator.&#xA;Why are MLPs then able to approximate functions well? Especially given the fact that most of the problems in coming up with candidate architectures, activation functions, etc. are &amp;lsquo;design problems&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Birds and Frogs in Science</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/birds-and-frogs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 20:20:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/birds-and-frogs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my fellow grad students shared a paper with me that turned out to be a great read. It was Professor Freeman Dyson&amp;rsquo;s article titled &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ams.org/notices/200902/rtx090200212p.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Birds and Frogs&lt;/a&gt;, that was the invited Einstein lecture at the American Mathematical Society.&#xA;Dyson talks about two categories of mathematicians (researchers) &amp;ndash; &lt;em&gt;birds&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;frogs&lt;/em&gt;.&#xA;While birds soar high, and get a view of the entire landscape, frogs tread tread deep, looking for details.&#xA;Dyson argues how both kinds are equally important for mathematics in particular, and science in general. He does not make a case for either being superior to the other, merely pointing out the differences between the research approach of the two.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real Analysis Notes</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/my-real-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2019 23:38:20 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/my-real-notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I took the course on Real Analysis, it made me very nervous. I was having fever dreams from the past when I took undergraduate real analysis and the epsilon-delta definitions just did not make a lot of sense. In retrospect, taking MA504 has been one of the best academic decisions, especially as an engineer.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has helped me a lot in how to concretely formulate definitions, and what &amp;lsquo;approaching&amp;rsquo;, &amp;rsquo;tending&amp;rsquo;, &amp;rsquo;limiting&amp;rsquo;, and other weasel words mean in a mathematical sense.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ML SoTA Resources</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/ml-sota/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2019 22:36:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/ml-sota/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The internet is filled with machine learning resources, and one of the most annoying things about them is the sheer volume.&#xA;There are many attempts at making compilations of papers, code, and current status quo in the vastly active, and fast paced field.&#xA;This post is to serve as a collection of my own where I will only post &lt;strong&gt;state of the art&lt;/strong&gt; in machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Most of these links are updated frequently and maintained by the community, and I have collected these &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; for reference. I am not trying to &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/927/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;create a new standard&lt;/a&gt;, but I will try to update the list if and when I come around doing that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>But why is Compactness important?</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/compactness2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 01:34:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/compactness2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/compactness&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; I touched upon the intuition behind topological compactness. We as engineers often hear about the word &amp;lsquo;compact&amp;rsquo; as a soft gatekeeping tool from doing serious mathematics. In this post we see why the understanding is very important for doing any mathematics, &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; as engineers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Recall the open cover definition of a compact set as the existence of a finite open subcover for any given open cover of the set. Note that the key words here are that the subcover is going to be finite, no matter which infinite cover we begin with. Let us keep that in mind. Now we often hear about compactness being a more subtle form of finiteness, or compactness abstracting the idea of being finite, or the two being related. The open cover definition lets us understand that slightly better. Open sets, being the building blocks of topology, give us a way to interact with &lt;em&gt;a specific class of sets in a finite manner&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It is this class of sets that we call compact.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compactness</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/compactness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2019 15:44:20 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/compactness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a non-mathematical note on what I understand about compactness and what it means for a set or a space to be compact.&#xA;The open cover definition is one that can be found in any textbook, but what does it &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; for a set to be &lt;em&gt;compact?&lt;/em&gt; Why are such sets called compact? And how do compact sets differ from those which are not?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think the terminology here is very carefully chosen. For once, mathematicians came up with a term that paints a succinct, abstract picture. To understand compactness,let us look at two other  properties: &lt;em&gt;limit points&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;closed sets&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instrumentals v/s Vocal Music</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/instrumental/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 16:02:49 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/instrumental/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I often talk to friends about music and musical preferences. This post is inspired by one such theme which often finds its way in most of these conversations: instrumental music v/s vocal music.&#xA;Or more precisely, &lt;em&gt;why listen to instrumental, or plain music, when you can have vocals accompanying the music&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This post is not from a musical perspective, but rather to emphasize on the entirely separate form of beauty inherent in instrumental music.&#xA;Personally, I think the term &lt;em&gt;instrumental&lt;/em&gt; music is somewhat a misnomer for this discussion. Let&amp;rsquo;s just call the two lyrical music, and lyric-less music.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Point Estimation Problem</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/pointestimate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 01:34:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/pointestimate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It might seem out of place that in the world of big data, finding a singular parameter&amp;rsquo;s estimate could be interesting. Quite the contrary &amp;ndash; &lt;strong&gt;point estimation problems&lt;/strong&gt; are one of the most ubiquitous parametric estimation problems that arise whether you are doing your Stat Inference 101 assignments, or dealing with $$10^8$$ rows in a parquet file. And so, I thought of making this post to look further into the point estimation problems, and when might one want to use which method.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
