<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Controls on Omanshu Thapliyal</title>
    <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/tags/controls/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Controls on Omanshu Thapliyal</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 11:07:46 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/tags/controls/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Technology Readiness Levels of AI methods</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/readiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 11:07:46 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/readiness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recent news of the SpaceX catching its Starship Super Heavy booster&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is quite discussed and marveled upon in the media, and rightly so.&#xA;Executing what was done can perhaps be explained as trying to catch a falling stick, then balancing it vertically, all while the stick is over 200 ft tall, weighs over 150 tonnes, spews fire, and costs over tens of millions of dollars.&#xA;One cannot but feel a little giddy as a controls engineering enthusiast over this massive success.&#xA;It makes me think why we are closer to automation in certain domains/problems than others? Why, for example, is your vacuum cleaning robot seemingly better at navigating in a cluttered environment than your possibly self-driving car? Why is the tremendous progress in machine learning &amp;amp; AI not permeating outside of our web lives as much as we expected in the early 2000&amp;rsquo;s?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why I am studying this: Data Driven Safety</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/data-driven-safety/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2022 12:32:31 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/data-driven-safety/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my attempt to try to motivate and justify why I am studying what I study, and to try to justify the title of my dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While most emphasis on safety has been provided from a model-driven perspective, data-driven approaches present a novel semi model-driven method by employing model-discovery. As data becomes more inexpensive, and system capabilities highly nonlinear, and often subject to parameter variations during mission, data-driven approaches are utilized more and more in controls engineering. Further, online and real-time applications increasingly require unknown models and nonlinear interactions to be learned for control synthesis. To this end, more established fields of system identification are increasingly utilizing data-driven models by using neural networks, autoregressive models, and other machine learning techniques. Due to the expressive nature of such machine learning techniques, they are  utilized to learn models of unknown dynamical systems from observed data sequences. In such approaches, a `discovered model&amp;rsquo; is arrived at using data, and employed to perform control design. Even though purely model-driven are slowly getting harder to apply to more recent, realistic, and complex scenarios, they provide a strong basis to study extensions of similar approaches to data-driven techniques for estimation and control. As a result, I attempt to utilize model-driven techniques and extend them to study safety and security properties of cyberphysical systems using data. Therefore, &lt;em&gt;my primary aim is to study data-driven approaches to safety, and data-driven vulnerabilities against cyberattacks, of complex control systems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Industry-Academia split in Control Systems</title>
      <link>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/split/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2019 12:32:31 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://omanshuthapliyal.github.io/blog/split/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I often wonder why the &amp;ldquo;cutting edge&amp;rdquo; research that we read about in the foremost scientific journals &amp;amp; conferences in Control Systems are never applied in the industry.&#xA;Because whenever we read/write papers, Section-I always tries to ground itself to industry and/or practical applications. However, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty well known that a majority of the controllers used in the industry are still tuned PIDs.&#xA;Even though sub-fields of modern control &amp;ndash; adaptive, and robust control are very mature and pretty old in their own rights, the real world&amp;rsquo;s inertia against using modern control techniques bears substantial weight.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
